なんば　むった
テキサス州ヒューストン…｡
Houston, Texas.
日本との時差 約１５時間｡
Around fifteen hours behind Japan.
眠い…｡
I'm falling asleep...
すいません 出口どこですか？
(掃除のおばさん)ウン！
Excuse me, where is the exit?
《私がアメリカに着いたその頃➡
As I arrived in America,
ひびと
日々人は
出かけようとしており…》
Hibito was heading out.
《そして…運命が
動き出そうとしていた》
And...
the wheels of fate had begun to turn.
《なぜ私がタダで
ナサ
ＮＡＳＡへ行けるのか｡➡
Why am I on an all-expense-paid trip to NASA?
それは 私が日々人の
兄だからである》
It's because I'm Hibito's brother.
しえん
《ＮＡＳＡには｢家族支援ﾌﾟﾛｸﾞﾗﾑ｣
なるものがある》
NASA offers a family support program.
《宇宙飛行士達がﾐｯｼｮﾝを終え
きかん
無事 地球に帰還するまでの間➡
Families are cared for
until astronauts complete their missions,
めんどう
家族の面倒を
見てくれるというものだ｡➡
and return safely to Earth.
けいげん
宇宙飛行士達の心配を軽減し➡
The goal is to reduce distractions,
にんむ
任務に集中して
もらうためである》
freeing astronauts to focus on their work.
《二次試験に落ちたかもしれない
このような状態で➡
I didn't like the idea of visiting Hibito when I still didn't know if I'd be passing the second exam.
日々人に会うのは
気が進まなかった…だが➡
But I couldn't turn down an invitation from NASA.
ゆうわく
ＮＡＳＡからの招待という誘惑に
打ち勝つことはできなかった》
NASA is calling to me...
うん？うん？
Space Brothers
Ah
This feels so good, different from usual
I have no idea what's going on
It feels so good
I never understand what's going on around me
Nothing makes sense to me
Full of questions
Feel so moon
I danced with you in a desert lit by the moon
I won't lose to the rabbit and fly high
I'll fly high
#05 Days of Missing
ヒューストン･サン･パーク…｡
Houston Sun Park...
あ ここで間違いないな｡
This is definitely the place.
≪ハッハッハッハッ…≫
Huh?
アポ？
Apo?
一文字違ったらアホか｡
What a dumb-sounding name.
可愛そうに｡もっとマシな
名前があっただろうに アポて…｡
Poor dog...
There are so many better possible names.
Seriously, Apo?
何だよ 何も持ってねぇぞ！
What?
I don't have anything for you!
エエイ！
タァ～トォ～テェ～！
Commence landing sequence!
(子供)着陸しま～す！
(子供)了解～！
Roger!
≪うお！≫
≪うわぁ！≫
宇宙人発見！宇宙人発見～！
Alien sighted! Alien sighted!
デェ～ッ！
ク～ン！
ヒッハッヒッハッ…うん!?
何でだ～！ハァハァハァ…｡
Why?
何で俺だぁ～！ハァハァハァ…｡
Why me?
There are other people around...
他にもいるだろ～！
クゥ～ン…｡
どんな臭いだよ｡
Do I smell like something?
アポ！
ワン！
Apo!
Huh?
よ～しよしよし｡
There, there, there...
フッ…お前の犬かよ そのアポは｡
So Apo is
your dog.
イエス
ＹＥＳ！
Yes!
ひっれえなぁ～｡
うん｡借家だけどね｡
This place is huge...
Yeah. I'm just renting it, though.
ん？ああ～ それ…｡
Oh, that's...
あっ！おっとそうだった｡
Oh! That's right...
I brought gifts.
土産 土産｡俺はいらねぇって
言ったんだけどさ➡
I wasn't going to bother,
母ちゃんが持ってけって
うるせ～から｡
but Mom kept nagging me about it.
見ろよ チンして食べる肉まんと
味付けのりと かきピーと➡
Here.
Microwaveable pork buns, flavored nori,
Persimmon P, and Korean kimchi that expires in two days.
しょうみきげん
賞味期限残り２日の韓国キムチ｡
｢アメリカ行ったら時差の分
期限延びるでしょ～｣だって｡
"America is behind, so you'll have more time before they go bad," she said.
全部ビミョーなところが
母ちゃんらしいな｡
I can definitely tell these are from Mom.
要するに自分がいらねぇもん
くれたってわけだ｡
She pretty much just gave you stuff she didn't want.
ガッガッガッガ…｡
I basically already guessed,
まさかとは思ったが やっぱり
｢アポロ｣からとって｢アポ｣かよ｡
but you named him "Apo" for "Apollo," right?
しょうりゃく
｢ロ｣ぐらい省略すんなよな～｡
Why bother shortening the -llo?
大体お前は 昔っから
ちっちゃ～いことを➡
Besides,
you've always been lax when it comes to little details.
くせ
面倒臭がる癖がある｡
Really?
そうかぁ？
だよ～｡例えば…｡
Yeah, for example...
カーテンのフックが
１個外れっぱなしになってる～｡
You missed a curtain hook.
電球１個切れっぱなし～｡
You have a dead light bulb.
ポスター剥がれかけ～｡
気付いているくせにやらない｡
Your poster has a corner sticking up.
You notice these, but you never bother to fix them.
まあな｡
I guess so.
部屋の中に
植物でも置きたいなぁ～｡
You'd like to keep a plant in your room.
でも水やり面倒臭いなぁ…と
迷った結果➡
But that would mean you'd have to water it.
And so...
このサボテン｡
さらによく見ると➡
You end up buying a cactus.
And on closer inspection,
値札をはがすのも
途中で諦めてる～｡
I see that you got sick of trying to remove the UPC...
There's probably something outside, in the yard, too.
庭にも何かあるんじゃね～か？
《こまけ～なぁ 相変わらず》
He's always so anal.
よし｡さてと…｡
Okay, then...
くつろいでる｡
You're making yourself at home.
最高じゃね～か この庭｡
Your backyard
rocks.
Oh, what are you doing?
ああ…何だっけ？それ｡
ああ 昔 ＤＶＤ一緒に見たろ｡
Oh, remember that movie we watched together?
こういう庭でやってるの
こうやって｡
With a guy, relaxing in his backyard, holding up his thumb?
何か意味あんの？それ｡
Was there some point?
さあ 意味とか知らねえけどな｡
Beats me.
There might not be any point.
直径3467km 地球からの距離
38万４千kmつってさ➡
The moon, with its 3,467-kilometer diameter,
is 384,000 kilometers from Earth.
バカでかい数字並べても
こっちから見たら➡
A bunch of big numbers that you can cover with your thumb.
親指に隠れちまう｡
そんな普通に生きてたら
絶対届かないような場所に➡
My little brother's about to head off to a place
もうすぐ自分の弟が
行くんだって考えたら➡
that's usually out of reach.
何かすげぇ…不思議だ｡
That's pretty crazy...
Like magic.
What're you talking about?
何言ってんだよ
ムッちゃんもあそこに行くんだろ｡
You'll make it there one day.
《簡単に言ってくれるぜ》
He makes it sound so easy!
昔 夏休みにさ➡
Remember that one summer vacation?
チャリで京都のばあちゃんちまで
行ったろ｡一緒に｡
When we rode our bikes to Grandma's house, in Kyoto?
何日かかったっけ？
３日…４日？
How many days did that take?
Three?
Four?
３日だよ｡
ああ そうだ そうだ｡
Three days.
Yeah, that's right.
京都まではチャリで
３日かかった｡
It took us three days to reach Kyoto by bike.
月までも
ロケットで３日だけどな｡
It takes three days to reach the moon by rocket.
When you think about it that way, the moon isn't out of reach.
そう考えりゃ
もう届かない場所じゃあない｡
楽勝で行ける気してきた？
Sound too easy for you now?
あのなぁ
この際はっきりいっとくけどな➡
Now, listen here...
Let me make something clear.
俺に行けるわけねえだろ？
今はもう 俺とお前じゃ➡
I'm not going to make it there.
We're in completely different situations now,
立場がとかこう…
状況がだな 違いすぎんだよ｡
completely different worlds.
And yours is
月までの距離感もな｡
a lot closer to the moon.
昔とは違うんだよ｡
Things are different now.
《お前にはわかんねぇだろ
日々人…》
You wouldn't understand, Hibito.
《今じゃ俺はどこに行っても➡
Everywhere I go, they call me "Nanba Hibito's older brother".
｢南波飛行士のお兄ちゃん｣と
呼ばれる…》
(面接官)((あれ？もしかして➡
Oh, is it possible that...
南波日々人飛行士の
ご親戚か何かですか？))
Could you be a relative of astronaut Nanba Hibito?
みぞぐちうわさ
(溝口)((噂になってますよ｡➡
Everyone's talking about you.
あの南波日々人飛行士の
お兄さんだって))
You're the astronaut Nanba Hibito's older brother?
あおたけ
(青竹)((ねぇ 南波君
今度日々人君に➡
Say, Nanba, would you please ask Hibito for an autograph?
サイン頼んどいて
もらえないかなぁ))
《誰も俺のことを｢南波六太｣とは
呼んでくれないんだぞ》
No one just calls me "Nanba Mutta".
あのさ…➡
Well,
all that's changed in my mind
今と昔で違うもんが
あるとすりゃ…➡
それはムッちゃんが…➡
is that you won't
昔みたいに
張り合わなくなったってことだ｡
even try to compete.
もっと張り合えよ｡
You're supposed to be my rival.
つまんねえよ｡
You're no fun now.
チキショー 日々人め｡
Stupid Hibito...
俺のことずっと
つまんねえって思ってたんなら➡
If you think
I'm not any fun,
もっと早く言ってくれよ～｡
you should have said something sooner.
《本当に頭のネジが
足りないという表現が➡
The phrase "he's got a screw loose" fits Hibito perfectly.
ジャストフィットだな
日々人には》
ペケだ ペケ｡ああ これもペケ｡
Wrong... Wrong. And that's wrong.
アット
ここ｢ａｔ｣が足りない｡
You're missing "at" here.
あっと！
だまれ｡ここも➡
At!
Quiet.
And you're missing the "K" from the start of "Knife."
ナイフの最初に｢ｋ｣が足りない｡
ｋ!?なんでｋ!?
読まないけど いるんだよ｡
"K"? Why "K"?
It's silent, but you still need it.
なにそれ？英語めんどくせ～｡
What the hell? English is a pain...
Don't whine over a single "K."
｢ｋ｣１個 面倒臭がるな｡➡
大体 お前は全体的に
なんか足りねぇんだよ｡
Besides, you have bigger worries.
あ～ 見ろよ
ここも１本足りねぇよ｡
Look here.
You're missing a stroke.
｢マイクがケンを
待っている｣が正解だろ？➡
The correct answer would be: "Mike is waiting for Ken."
Mike is samuraiing Ken
We are on a train.
さむら
｢マイクがケンを…侍っている｣➡
"Mike is
samuraiing Ken..."
斬るのか マイクがケンを｡
Is Mike going to cut down Ken?
Mike is samuraiing Ken
We are on a train.
MIKE
KEN
≪トリャア～！≫
マイク キル ケン？
Mike kill Ken?
Quiet!
うるせぇ！
ちょっと合ってること言うな｡
It's only half-right!
せっかくシャロンおばちゃんに
英語教わってるんだから➡
We have Aunt Sharon to teach us English,
ちゃんとやろうぜ｡
so work harder.
She'll cry if she sees your grades!
こんな点数じゃ泣くぞ｡
あい｡
Okay.
現在
《私の弟は昔…勉強なんて
全く出来ないヤツだった｡➡
My brother was always a bad student.
Back then, I had to teach him everything.
あの頃は勉強という勉強は全て
私が教える日々だった｡➡
だから 日々人が中学で
別人のようにグングン成績が➡
So when Hibito's grades suddenly improved in middle school,
上がっていった時 私が勉強を
教えてやったおかげだと思った｡➡
I thought it was thanks to me.
だけど どうも
そうじゃなかった｡➡
But that wasn't it.
突然 日々人は私より
成績が良くなったのだ》
Suddenly, Hibito's grades were actually better than mine.
(手紙:声)｢先にｼﾞｮﾝｿﾝ宇宙ｾﾝﾀｰに
行ってくる…➡
"I'm going to the Jonson Space Center.
Come down after you eat breakfast.
朝食 食ったら来いよ 朝食は…｣｡
Your breakfast is..."
Damn it...
《くっそ！わざわざ
英語で書きやがって｡➡
He wrote the note in English!
試してんのか～ 俺を!?》
Is he trying to test me?!
ガラガラ…ペッ！
Further...
ジョンソン
《しかも…Johnsonの
｢ｈ｣が抜けてんだよ！》
He forgot the "h" in "Johnson."
誰が行くかよ…ハフッ｡
I'm not going.
((もっと 張り合えよ
…つまんねぇよ))
You're supposed to be my rival.
You're no fun now.
やっぱり
訓練のマニュアルか…｡
So this really is a training manual...
両面コピーで
この枚数は恐ろしいな～｡
They print it on both sides, and it's still this many pages?
《あいつ…
これ全部 読んだのか？》
Has he read the whole thing?
Apo...
アポ…｡
Ah!
(オジー)君…｡アッハハハ…➡
You?
もしかして君 六太か？
そうだろう？
Are you Mutta? You must be.
(オバー)そうよ 六太よ｡六太｡
Yes! It's Mutta! Mutta!
なっ…なんだよ…｡
Wh-What is this?
ここのホットドッグは
別に美味くはないんだけどね➡
The hot dogs here aren't anything special,
but Apo loves them.
アポは大好きなんだよ｡
あの…いつもスミスさん夫妻が
アポの散歩を？
Uh, do you always walk Apo, Mr. and Mrs. Smith?
僕たちだけじゃないよ｡
日々人んちの両隣も犬を飼っとる｡
We aren't the only ones.
The families living on either side of Hibito also have dogs.
みんなで交代でやってるのよ｡
日々人が訓練の日はね｡
We take turns on the days when Hibito has his training.
I'm sorry for the trouble
何だか すみません｡弟が皆さんに
迷惑をおかけしているようで…｡
my brother is causing you all.
We really enjoy walking Apo.
(オジー)みんな好きで
やってるんだよ｡
えっ!?…そうなんですか？
Really?
ああ｡日々人は迷惑どころか
我々 年寄りに元気をくれるぞ｡
Sure.
Hibito isn't any trouble. In fact, he helps energize us old-timers.
宇宙の話や
あなたとの思い出話とかね…➡
He tells us stories about space, and his childhood with you.
いろいろ 聞いているのよ｡
We've heard all kinds of things.
ちゃんと正しく
伝わってるかどうか心配です｡
I'm worried whether he's been telling you the right things.
Eh?
いつも何か…
ちょっと抜けてるんです｡
He always seems to miss something.
日々人に
ジャストフィットする言葉は…｡
The perfect phrase to describe Hibito is...
(ｽﾀｯﾌ)サムライボーイ お疲れ！
Good work, Samurai Boy.
｢頭のネジが一本足りない｣です｡
...He's got a screw loose
in his head.
月の重力も楽しいもんだろう｡
It must be fun to experience how gravity on the moon feels.
ああ｡これで
あと 水がなけりゃな｡
Yeah.
I sure wish there wasn't any water, though.
えっ!?ムッちゃん
まだ 来てね～の？
What? Mu hasn't shown up?
No, not yet.
(受付)ええ…まだ｡
な…何やってんだよ｡
Wh-What is he doing?
まさか…
メモが読めなかったとか？
Did he not understand my note?
って…んなわけね～よな｡
No, that can't be it...
おう！おけ～り 日々人！
Hey! Welcome home, Hibito!
どうだ～！
How about this?
晩飯 作っといてやったぞ～！
名付けて…➡
I made dinner!
I call this...
｢賞味期限ギリギリキムチ定食｣｡
my "soon-to-expire kimchi dinner"!
はっきり言って
料理の腕は 俺の方が上だ｡
Honestly, my cooking is a notch above yours.
山の手線の全駅名も
俺の方が早く言える!!
And I can name every station on the Yamate Line faster than you!
あと…Ｊリーグの選手名鑑
2025年度版は すでに暗記済み！
And I've already memorized the 2025 compendium of J. League players!
さっきから何 言ってんの？
What are you talking about?
張り合ってんだよ｡
I-I'm competing with you.
You're the one who said...
夕べ お前が…｡
そういうことじゃね～だろ｡
That's not what I meant.
くち
口で張り合って どうすんだよ｡
That's all just talk.
なっ…んん…｡
Fine!
じゃあ モノマネで勝負だ!!
Let's see who can do a better impression!
俺なんて ボール蹴るふりする
だけでラモス似って言われるぞ！
Give me a ball to kick,
and I'm the spittin' image of Ramos.
Watch this...
行っくぞ～!!
それも違うだろ｡
That's not it, either.
ま…まあ食えや｡
俺は ちょっと寝るわ｡
W-Well, enjoy your dinner.
I'm going to bed.
ムッちゃん！
Mu.
明日は見学来いよ…
何しに こっちまで来たんだよ｡
Come down to the center tomorrow.
Why else did you bother to make this trip?
《やっぱ違うよな～
わかってたけど…➡
That was wrong...
I did know, though.
あれじゃ 小４だ…
小４の俺で挑んでどうする》
That was just like in fourth grade.
Why would I use my fourth-grade self to compete with him?
He's got a screw loose?
Yes.
((ええ…日本では
日々人みたいに➡
That's how we describe people like Hibito, who seem to be missing something.
抜けているヤツのことを
そう言うんです))
((ハハハハハッ…なるほど｡
何か足りないんだね～))
I see, so he's missing something...
((そうなんです))
(オジー)((じゃあ 僕もそうだ))
That's right.
Then I'm the same way.
(オバー)((私もね))
Huh?
So am I.
Each of us is missing something.
((誰だって
何か足りないもんだよ｡➡
六太 僕らは君に
初めて会った気がしない))
Mutta, we feel like we've known you a long time.
((あなたのことは日々人から
聞いてただけなのにね))
Even though we've only heard about you from Hibito.
Once, I asked him the following question:
((いつだったか
彼に質問したことがある))
((｢六太は今
何をしてるんだい？｣って｡➡
"What is Mutta doing right now?"
And...
そしたら こう答えた｡
｢ムッちゃんは今頃 日本で➡
This was his answer:
"Mu is in Japan, preparing to be an astronaut."
宇宙飛行士になる
準備をしてるはずだよ｣と｡➡
何度か聞いたけど
答えはいつも同じだった｡➡
Each time I asked, his answer stayed the same:
"Mutta is preparing."
｢六太は準備中｣
｢六太は準備中｣…➡
"Mutta is preparing." "Mutta is preparing..."
｢六太は準備中｣))
((必ず 君が来ると思っていた
日々人にとって➡
Every day that Hibito spent alone,
自分だけが進んでいる毎日は➡
certain that you would join him
｢足りない日々｣だったんじゃ
ないのかな～…))
was a day of missing for him, see?
フッ…フッ…｡
ウッ｡ウハッ…ウッ…｡
《兄とは常に…弟の先を
行ってなければ…ならない》
An older brother is...
always supposed to be ahead...
of his younger brother...
ウッ…兄とは…｡ウハッ｡
An older brother is...
ハァ…ハァ…ハァ…｡
Damn...
くそっ…ん!?
≪日々人～！日々人～！≫
Hibito!
≪ほら見ろよ！
こっち こっち!!≫
Look at this!
O-Over here!
ウッ…ウッ…｡
おっせ～ぞ 日々人！
いつまで寝てんだよ～！
You slept in, Hibito!
How long are you gonna sleep?
現在
(手紙:声)｢日々人へ…今日
行かなかったのは➡
"To Hibito,
The reason I didn't go was that I had terrible bed hair.
寝グセが ひどかったからだ｡
明日は俺もＮＡＳＡへ行く｡➡
Tomorrow I'll go to NASA, too.
しかも お前より早起きしてな…｣｡
On top of that, I'll wake up earlier than you!"
プッ…｡フフッ…｡
さて…南波六太君と沢木学君…➡
Now, we have Nanba Mutta and Sawaki Manabu.
どちらか１人を
｢落とす｣というのであれば…｡
If I had to cut one of them...
(田沼)私は迷いなく…
南波君を落とします｡
I would immediately pick
Nanba.
The stars I admired were too bright for me
so I quietly closed my eyes
I have faith in you, as you stand alone, full of doubts
I'm right here, next to you
Come now, take my hand and hold it tight
If you do, we will always
have hope, shine with light
and overcome whatever we might face
Do you see how wonderful this world is
and how our future unfolds?
Even the tears we shed and could not put into words
will one day dry up, I am sure
One by one the smiles spread
and ascend towards the starlit sky
＜ﾋｭｰｽﾄﾝにやってきた俺は ついに
聖地ジョンソン宇宙センターへ➡
Next time, on
Space Brothers
#06 Et Cetera in My Head
After arriving in Houston, I finally visit the aerospace Mecca, the Johnson Space Center!
…来たものの
みんな 日々人 日々人＞
But everyone's talking about Hibito...
＜どんだけ人気者だよ＞
Just how popular is he?
＜僕にとって
兄は 自慢の存在です＞
Personally, I'm very proud of my older brother.
＜はあ!?そんな中
日本から最悪の知らせ＞
Huh?!
And then I get terrible news from Japan.
＜俺が頭突きした
前の会社の役員が➡
The exec I headbutted at my former company called JAXA to tell them I'm a bad candidate.
｢俺なんか
宇宙飛行士にふさわしくない｣と➡
ジャクサ
ＪＡＸＡに
わざわざ連絡したらしい＞
Next time, on Space Brothers:
"Et Cetera in My Head."
＜もう100％ 救いはない＞
I don't have a snowball's chance in Hell...
パンパカパ～ン！
This Week's Space Photo
This week's space photo!
今週の宇宙写真です！
スッゲ～!!
Awesome!